(This drama is a work of fiction created based on historical facts.)
(هذه الدراما عمل خيالي تم إنشاؤه بناءً على حقائق تاريخية).
(Most of the details and depictions of the characters are fictional.)
(معظم تفاصيل وتصورات الشخصيات خيالية).
Are you okay?
هل أنت بخير؟
Lady Gil Chae.
سيدة جيل تشاي.
Watch out, my dear!
احترس يا عزيزي!
Are you okay?
هل أنت بخير؟
You are not hurt?
أنت لا تتأذى؟
You are bleeding.
أنت تنزف.
By the way, Lady Gil Chae.
بالمناسبة ، سيدة جيل تشاي.
Did you just call me...
هل ناديتي...
"my dear?"
"عزيزي؟"
(My Dearest)
(أعز ما عندي)
Once I swing my club,
بمجرد تأرجح النادي الخاص بي ،
the heads of the intruders will rock here,
ستهتز رؤوس المتسللين هنا ،
rock there, and rock back and forth.
صخرة هناك ، والصخرة ذهابا وإيابا.
We would have to duck from all their flying heads.
كان علينا أن نبتعد عن كل رؤوسهم الطائرة.
- Right? - How sly.
- يمين؟  - كيف خبيث.
Tell me about it.
حدثني عنها.
I thought he was a coward since he refused to join the army.
اعتقدت أنه كان جبانًا لأنه رفض الالتحاق بالجيش.
What a swindler.
يا له من نصاب.
A swindler like him...
محتال مثله ...
grows on me.
ينمو علي.
I want to be swindled from time to time.
أريد أن أُخدع من وقت لآخر.
Me too.
أنا أيضاً.
In that case,
في هذه الحالة،
do you not have Yeon Jun's news after splitting up with them?
أليس لديك أخبار يون جون بعد الانفصال معهم؟
Do not worry. I am sure he made it into the fortress safely.
لا تقلق.  أنا متأكد من أنه وصل إلى القلعة بأمان.
I hope so.
أتمنى ذلك.
He must be safe.
يجب أن يكون بأمان.
The intruders must not have expected Joseon to have such a club...
لا بد أن الدخلاء لم يتوقعوا أن يكون لجوسون مثل هذا النادي ...
and called me "The Club of Joseon."
ودعوني "نادي جوسون".
I will be called "The Club of Joseon," do you not think?
سأدعى "نادي جوسون" ألا تعتقد ذلك؟
- As if. - I am telling the truth.
- كما لو.  - انا اقول الحقيقة.
I heard something strange earlier.
سمعت شيئًا غريبًا في وقت سابق.
Someone called me...
اتصل بي شخص ما ...
her husband.
زوجها.
Who was that?
من كان هذا؟
Well, I wonder who.
حسنًا ، أتساءل من.
Was it not you?
الم تكن انت
"Watch out,"
"احترس،"
"my dear!"
"عزيزي!"
I think you said that.
أعتقد أنك قلت ذلك.
My goodness.
رباه.
You must have heard things out of fear for the intruders.
لابد أنك سمعت أشياء خوفا على الدخلاء.
How strange. I definitely heard it.
كم هذا غريب.  لقد سمعت ذلك بالتأكيد.
Jong Jong.
الشباب الشباب.
You heard it, yes?
هل سمعته ، نعم؟
Well...
حسنًا...
Gu Jam.
قو جام.
Did you hear it?
هل سمعته؟
I mean...
أعني...
Let me ask you, Lady Eun Ae.
اسمح لي أن أسألك ، سيدة إيون آي.
- Yes? - Did you hear it?
- نعم؟  - هل سمعته؟
"Watch out, my dear!"
"احترس يا عزيزي!"
Yes, I did.
نعم فعلت.
Have you all lost it?
هل فقدت كل ذلك؟
My lady.
سيدتي.
Hey.
يا.
Why are you so dense as her servant?
لماذا أنت كثيفة جدا مثل خادمها؟
Oh, my...
أوه ، يا ...
Goodness.
صلاح.
Why did you say that? Why did you...
لما قلت ذلك؟  لماذا فعلت...
tell me, "Watch out, my dear?"
قل لي ، "احترس يا عزيزتي؟"
Lest I got hurt?
لئلا أتأذى؟
Or were you afraid that I would die?
أم كنت تخشى أن أموت؟
Wait, that is not the point.
انتظر ، ليس هذا هو الهدف.
Why exactly did you call me your "dear?"
لماذا بالضبط مناداتي بك "عزيزتي؟"
I see. Deep down, you must have wanted me as your husband.
أرى.  في أعماقك ، لابد أنك أردتني أن أكون زوجك.
Me?
أنا؟
Want you?
أريدك؟
As my husband?
كزوجي؟
What utter nonsense.
ما هذا الهراء المطلق.
If I have to marry you,
إذا كان علي الزواج منك ،
I would rather shave my head and be a nun...
أفضل أن أحلق رأسي وأن أكون راهبة ...
I am afraid it is a shame.
أخشى أنه عار.
Did I not tell you previously?
ألم أخبرك سابقا؟
I...
أنا...
am not interested in marriage.
لست مهتمًا بالزواج.
My motto is, well...
شعاري هو ، حسنًا ...
Courting is essential,
المغازلة أمر ضروري ،
marriage is a choice.
الزواج اختيار.
Something like that?
شئ مثل هذا؟
Is that why you have lovers all across the country?
هل هذا هو سبب وجود عشاق في جميع أنحاء البلاد؟
Because you can never stop courting?
لأنه لا يمكنك التوقف عن المغازلة؟
- I have lovers across the country? - Yes.
- لدي عشاق في جميع أنحاء البلاد؟  - نعم.
It is an open secret.
إنه سر مكشوف.
Did you think I would not know?
هل تعتقد أنني لن أعرف؟
No wonder.
لا عجب.
Now I see why the Neunggun-ri ladies were so snarky towards me.
الآن أرى لماذا كانت سيدات Neunggun-ri متغطرسة تجاهي.
Then why...
إذن لماذا...
do you want me...
هل تريدني...
as your husband?
كزوجك
I did not do it on purpose!
لم أفعلها عمدا!
By accident, I...
بالصدفة ، أنا ...
"By accident?"
"بالصدفة؟"
I see you finally remember.
أراك تتذكر أخيرًا.
You definitely...
أنت بالتأكيد ...
called me "dear."
دعاني "عزيزي".
All right?
حسنًا؟
My lady.
سيدتي.
Do not be shy. The fact that you spurted that out...
لا تكن خجولا.  حقيقة أنك أطلقت ذلك ...
means that deep down, you must think of me...
يعني ذلك في أعماقك ، يجب أن تفكر بي ...
as someone worthy to be your husband.
كشخص يستحق أن يكون زوجك.
And so,
و حينئذ،
even though I do not intend to get married,
على الرغم من أنني لا أنوي الزواج ،
if you really want me to be your husband...
إذا كنت تريدني حقًا أن أكون زوجك ...
You must have looked like Young Master Yeon Jun.
لا بد أنك بدوت مثل السيد الشاب يون جون.
That was why I called you "my dear."
لهذا دعوتك "عزيزتي".
Goodness.
صلاح.
I would not have said that to a misogamist.
لم أكن لأقول ذلك لكره الزواج.
You thought I was Young Master Yeon Jun?
كنت تعتقد أنني كنت السيد الشاب يون جون؟
- Madam Bang Doo. - Okay.
- سيدتي بانغ دو.  - تمام.
We will be able to sleep warm tonight.
سنكون قادرين على النوم دافئ الليلة.
The baby is such a lucky child.
الطفل مثل هذا الطفل المحظوظ.
Shall we call him "Dae Bok?"
هل ندعوه "بوك"؟
Dae Bok?
داي بوك؟
Why is he so beautiful?
لماذا هو جميل جدا؟
He must not take after his mother.
يجب ألا يأخذ بعد والدته.
I agree.
أنا موافق.
What is on your mind?
ماذا يدور في ذهنك؟
Young Master Yeon Jun.
السيد الشاب يون Jun.
You are such a petty man.
أنت رجل تافه.
I am serious.
انا جاد.
I wonder if Young Master Yeon Jun...
أتساءل عما إذا كان السيد الشاب يون جون ...
is thinking about the two ladies waiting for him.
يفكر في السيدتين تنتظره.
Or...
أو...
is he only thinking about the King?
هل يفكر فقط في الملك؟
That just crossed my mind.
هذا فقط خطرت ببالي.
In any case,
على أي حال،
thank you.
شكرًا لك.
For telling me to flee,
لقول لي أن أهرب ،
and for saving us today.
ومن أجل إنقاذنا اليوم.
I am just grateful, that is all.
أنا فقط ممتن ، هذا كل شيء.
Do you really feel grateful?
هل تشعر حقا بالامتنان؟
In that case,
في هذه الحالة،
can I...
هل استطيع...
kiss you this time...
أقبلك هذه المرة ...
Why, you...
لماذا أنت...
I am not such a serious man.
أنا لست مثل هذا الرجل الجاد.
Serious feelings like your love for Yeon Jun...
مشاعر جدية مثل حبك ليون جون ...
are just...
منصف...
too much for me.
كثيرا بالنسبة لي.
What I truly want...
ما أريده حقًا ...
is your warm lips...
شفتيك دافئة ...
Even if I want to be nice to you,
حتى لو أردت أن أكون لطيفًا معك ،
I utterly cannot.
أنا لا أستطيع.
You are such a lousy, good-for-nothing lowlife.
أنت مثل هذا الرديء ، وحياة منخفضة جيدة مقابل لا شيء.
What a lousy, good-for-nothing lowlife.
يا لها من وضيع رديء ، جيد مقابل لا شيء.
I will leave behind a horse and a wagon.
سأترك ورائي حصان وعربة.
Please carry Madam Bang Doo.
من فضلك احمل سيدتي بانغ دو.
- All right. - Where are you going?
- حسنًا.  - إلى أين تذهب؟
Dae Bok.
داي بوك.
Lady Gil Chae is scary, yes?
السيدة جيل تشاي مخيفة ، أليس كذلك؟
Here.
هنا.
I have to continue chasing the enemies.
لا بد لي من الاستمرار في مطاردة الأعداء.
What about us?
ماذا عنا؟
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
You can just continue to do what you have been doing.
يمكنك فقط الاستمرار في فعل ما كنت تفعله.
You even know how to wield a blade now, do you not?
أنت تعرف حتى كيف تستخدم النصل الآن ، أليس كذلك؟
You should not lose such a boon as this.
يجب ألا تفقد نعمة كهذه.
I never once used this...
لم أستخدم هذا مرة واحدة ...
My lady,
سيدتي،
I am proud of you.
أنا فخور بك.
What did I tell you?
ماذا أخبرتك؟
You are more trustworthy...
أنت أكثر ثقة ...
than a bunch of small-boned scholars.
من حفنة من صغار العلماء.
Come to think of it,
تعال نفكر بها،
you also saved my life.
أنت أيضا أنقذت حياتي.
Thanks to you,
شكرا لك،
who mistook me for Young Master Yeon Jun,
الذي ظنني أنه السيد الشاب يون جون ،
I was able to avoid the attack.
تمكنت من تجنب الهجوم.
Quit making fun of me.
توقف عن السخرية مني.
Once you cut your wisdom teeth,
بمجرد قطع أسنانك الحكيمة ،
I will stop making fun of you.
سأتوقف عن السخرية منك.
- Let us go. - Wait.
- دعنا نذهب.  - انتظر.
I am leaving.
أنا مغادر.
I do not care.
انا لا اهتم.
I wonder if they were able to get up the mountain.
أتساءل عما إذا كانوا قادرين على صعود الجبل.
Jong Jong has a weak body.
جونغ جونغ لديه جسم ضعيف.
You are so mean.
انت لئيم.
Do not worry. She is stronger than you.
لا تقلق.  هي أقوى منك.
Are they refugees?
هل هم لاجئون؟
They look like they have been starving...
يبدو أنهم كانوا يتضورون جوعا ...
What?
ماذا؟
- Have some. - Thank you.
- لدينا بعض.  - شكرًا لك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Eat up.
أكل.
I heard General Jung Se Kyu's royal forces suffered a crushing defeat.
سمعت أن القوات الملكية للجنرال جونغ سي كيو عانت من هزيمة ساحقة.
So...
لذا...
where were you headed?
الى اين كنت متجه
To His Majesty.
إلى جلالة الملك.
Before that, we are going to attack the intruders...
قبل ذلك سنهاجم المتسللين ...
and offer a trophy head to His Majesty.
وقدم درعًا تذكاريًا لجلالة الملك.
(Trophy head: the head of an enemy that has been cut during war)
(رأس الكأس: رأس العدو الذي قُطع أثناء الحرب)
I heard General Kim Jun Ryong's army...
سمعت جيش الجنرال كيم جون ريونغ ...
is camped out on Mount Gwanggyo.
يقام على جبل جوانجيو.
Do you want to join us?
هل ترغب في الإنضمام إلينا؟
Did I not tell you? I have no interest in saving the King.
ألم أخبرك؟  ليس لدي مصلحة في إنقاذ الملك.
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
where are Young Master Soon Yak and the others?
أين السيد الشاب سون ياك والآخرون؟
It has not been long since they went to battle.
لم يمض وقت طويل على ذهابهم إلى المعركة.
I cannot believe they already died.
لا أصدق أنهم ماتوا بالفعل.
They are like sheep without a shepherd.
هم مثل الغنم بلا راع.
You are right.
أنت محق.
At this rate, they will all end up dead like Young Master Soon Yak.
بهذا المعدل ، سينتهي بهم المطاف جميعًا ميتين مثل السيد الشاب سون ياك.
I ran into Lady Eun Ae earlier.
قابلت السيدة إيون آي في وقت سابق.
She was separated from her parents,
انفصلت عن والديها ،
and the ladies were fleeing on their own.
وكانت السيدات يهربن بمفردهن.
Is everyone safe?
هل الجميع آمنون؟
That brings me to my point.
هذا يقودني إلى وجهة نظري.
What do you think of giving up on saving the King...
ما رأيك في الاستسلام لإنقاذ الملك ...
and protecting Lady Eun Ae instead?
وحماية السيدة إيون آي بدلاً من ذلك؟
I cannot do that.
لا أستطيع أن أفعل ذلك.
I do not think we will be able to defeat the intruders.
لا أعتقد أننا سنكون قادرين على هزيمة المتسللين.
I could die...
من الممكن أن أموت...
before I even get to see His Majesty.
قبل أن أتمكن حتى من رؤية جلالة الملك.
Like Soon Yak.
مثل ياك قريبا.
But...
لكن...
I do not know how to live a life that is different from what I have learned.
لا أعرف كيف أعيش حياة مختلفة عما تعلمته.
For my entire life, I learned that it is my duty...
طوال حياتي تعلمت أن من واجبي ...
to fight for the nation when it is in danger.
للقتال من أجل الأمة عندما تكون في خطر.
A woman obeying a man, a child serving his parents,
امرأة تطيع الرجل ، والطفل في خدمة والديه ،
and a subject being loyal to the King are beautiful orders that should be kept.
والموضوع المخلص للملك هي أوامر جميلة يجب الحفاظ عليها.
In return, a man should protect his woman and parents should protect their children.
في المقابل ، يجب على الرجل حماية امرأته وعلى الوالدين حماية أطفالهم.
And the King and the scholar-officials should protect the people.
وعلى الملك والعلماء المسؤولين حماية الناس.
I am going to die while protecting the King.
سأموت وأنا أحمي الملك.
If I die for the King,
إذا مت من أجل الملك ،
he will protect the people.
سوف يحمي الناس.
That is the only thing I trust.
هذا هو الشيء الوحيد الذي أثق به.
Let us go to Mount Gwanggyo together.
دعونا نذهب إلى جبل جوانغيو معًا.
We are not going to save the King.
لن ننقذ الملك.
Then?
ثم؟
Bul Kang.
بول كانغ.
I...
أنا...
did not know I would be doing stuff like this.
لم أكن أعرف أنني سأفعل أشياء مثل هذه.
Goodness.
صلاح.
Look at the calluses on my hands.
انظر إلى المسامير على يدي.
My hands are so dry and dark.
يدي جافة ومظلمة للغاية.
Then should I do it?
ثم يجب أن أفعل ذلك؟
Will you?
سوف تفعل؟
Why you little...
لماذا أنت ضئيل...
It is smoking because you put in wet branches.
إنه يدخن لأنك تضع أغصانًا مبللة.
Madam Bang Doo, I told you not to come out in the cold.
سيدتي بانغ دو ، أخبرتك ألا تخرج في البرد.
You blanched the dried radish greens, right?
لقد قمت بتبييض خضار الفجل المجففة ، أليس كذلك؟
When you blanch the dried radish greens,
عندما تبيض خضار الفجل المجففة ،
add a pinch of salt, then squeeze the water out.
أضف قليلًا من الملح ثم اعصر الماء.
Then add soybean paste and sesame oil...
ثم نضيف معجون فول الصويا وزيت السمسم ...
and mix everything together.
وامزج كل شيء معًا.
And finish it by boiling it.
وننهيها بغليها.
Okay?
تمام؟
The thing is,
الشيء هو،
I have never eaten anything like this in my life.
لم أتناول شيئًا كهذا أبدًا في حياتي.
Is that so?
هل هذا صحيح؟
- Then I should eat your fill... - I have never eaten this before,
- ثم يجب أن آكل حشو الخاص بك ... - لم آكل هذا من قبل ،
so it is fascinating.
لذلك فهي رائعة.
I see you did not add sesame oil.
اراك لم تضيف زيت السمسم.
You need sesame oil to get rid of the bad smell...
تحتاج زيت السمسم للتخلص من الرائحة الكريهة ...
and make it more flavorful...
وجعلها أكثر لذيذ ...
We have no sesame oil.
ليس لدينا زيت سمسم.
Goodness. There, there.
صلاح.  هناك هناك.
At this rate,
بهذا المعدل،
we will probably starve to death.
ربما سنموت جوعا.
The reinforcements are here?
التعزيزات هنا؟
General, we are here after receiving your request...
عام نحن هنا بعد استلام طلبك ...
Is this all of you?
هل هذا كلكم؟
Sorry?
آسف؟
It is an ambush!
إنه كمين!
General, it is an ambush.
بشكل عام ، إنه كمين.
Can you fight?
هل يمكنك القتال؟
Yes, we can.
نعم نستطيع.
But we just came.
لكننا جئنا للتو.
They must enjoy fighting.
يجب أن يستمتعوا بالقتال.
I know, right?
أنا أوافق؟
They must be eager to get themselves killed.
يجب أن يكونوا حريصين على قتل أنفسهم.
You better stay on your toes if you do not want to die by their hands.
من الأفضل أن تبقى على أصابع قدميك إذا كنت لا تريد أن تموت بأيديهم.
What are you saying? I am "The Club of Joseon."
ماذا تقول؟  أنا "نادي جوسون".
Hey, wait for me!
مهلا ، انتظرني!
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
This is our horse!
هذا هو حصاننا!
So it had an owner.
لذلك كان لها مالك.
Where are you going?
إلى أين تذهب؟
I heard all of the defeated royal forces...
سمعت كل القوات الملكية المهزومة ...
are gathering around General Kim Jun Ryong on Mount Gwanggyo.
يتجمعون حول الجنرال كيم جون ريونج على جبل جوانجيو.
We are going there as well.
نحن نذهب هناك أيضا.
You are going near the battlefield?
أنت ذاهب بالقرب من ساحة المعركة؟
You will be in more danger.
ستكون في خطر أكبر.
But still, we should be near our military to feel safe.
لكن مع ذلك ، يجب أن نكون بالقرب من جيشنا لنشعر بالأمان.
My sons volunteered to join the army.
تطوع أبنائي للالتحاق بالجيش.
I should go and help.
يجب أن أذهب وأساعد.
I am going to aid in treating the wounded soldiers.
سوف أساعد في علاج الجنود الجرحى.
Anyway, do not think of taking this horse with you.
على أي حال ، لا تفكر في اصطحاب هذا الحصان معك.
Why are they so concerned about others?
لماذا هم مهتمون جدا بالآخرين؟
They should just worry about fleeing.
عليهم فقط القلق بشأن الفرار.
I want to go too.
اريد ان اذهب ايضا
What?
ماذا؟
I want to go and help.
أريد أن أذهب وأساعد.
I do not want to keep fleeing like a coward.
لا أريد الاستمرار في الفرار مثل الجبان.
Hey, do not even think about it.
مهلا ، حتى لا تفكر في ذلك.
You heard the rumors.
سمعت الشائعات.
General Jung Se Kyu was defeated,
الجنرال جونغ سي كيو هُزم ،
so the volunteer army has been split up.
لذلك تم تقسيم جيش المتطوعين.
Young Master Yeon Jun might be in Mount Gwanggyo.
قد يكون السيد الشاب يون جون في جبل جوانغيو.
Mount Gwanggyo is near Mount Heomcheon.
يقع Mount Gwanggyo بالقرب من Mount Heomcheon.
Still, we cannot go.
ومع ذلك ، لا يمكننا الذهاب.
This is not what I was born to do.
ليس هذا ما ولدت لأفعله.
Why did these darn men have to come here?
لماذا هؤلاء الرجال الرتق يجب أن يأتوا إلى هنا؟
Sound of flowers, my foot.
صوت الزهور ، قدمي.
I should be heating up my back, lying down on a warm spot.
يجب أن أقوم بتدفئة ظهري ، مستلقية على مكان دافئ.
Right.
يمين.
I will just let him die.
سوف أتركه يموت.
Darn it.
رتقها.
Open your eyes!
افتح عينيك!
It hurts.
هذا مؤلم.
Hold it.
أمسك به.
When will I get better?
متى سأتحسن؟
I will not put up with this any longer.
لن أتحمل هذا بعد الآن.
Mother.
الأم.
What are you doing? Hold him.
ماذا تفعل؟  امسكه.
Mother, save me.
أمي ، أنقذني.
Mother.
الأم.
You are still there, right?
ما زلت هناك ، أليس كذلك؟
I am not your mother.
أنا لست والدتك.
You are here.
أنت هنا.
Mother.
الأم.
Do not go anywhere.
لا تذهب إلى أي مكان.
I am not your mother.
أنا لست والدتك.
Fine.
بخير.
I will not go anywhere. I will be here.
لن أذهب إلى أي مكان.  سوف اكون هنا.
Is the physician here?
هل الطبيب هنا؟
- Excuse me. - Where is the physician?
- اعذرني.  - أين الطبيب؟
Young Master Yeon Jun.
السيد الشاب يون Jun.
How...
كيف...
Young Master Yeon Jun!
السيد الشاب يون جون!
Young Master Yeon Jun! Oh, dear.
السيد الشاب يون جون!  يا عزيزي.
Get up.
استيقظ.
- Young Master Yeon Jun! What do we do? - Young Master Yeon Jun!
- السيد الشاب يون جون!  ماذا نفعل؟  - السيد الشاب يون جون!
Help him.
ساعده.
Lie down here.
استلقي هنا.
- Physician! - Young Master Yeon Jun!
- الطبيب المعالج!  - السيد الشاب يون جون!
Young Master Yeon Jun!
السيد الشاب يون جون!
What?
ماذا؟
Hey, you!
يا هذا!
You have to tell me what happened.
عليك أن تخبرني بما حدث.
I should be asking you.
يجب أن أسألك.
You said you would refuge beyond the mountains, so why are you here?
قلت إنك ستلجأ إلى ما وراء الجبال ، فلماذا أنت هنا؟
Eun Ae insisted on coming along,
أصرّت إيون إي على القدوم ،
saying she wanted to help the wounded soldiers.
قائلة إنها تريد مساعدة الجنود الجرحى.
I knew it.
كنت أعرف.
The high and mighty Lady Gil Chae would not be interested in helping others.
السيدة "جيل تشاي" العالية والقوية لن تكون مهتمة بمساعدة الآخرين.
Do you even realize how many lives I have saved here?
هل تدرك حتى عدد الأرواح التي أنقذتها هنا؟
Just a while ago, a young soldier...
منذ فترة وجيزة ، جندي شاب ...
tightly held onto my hand, begging for his life.
تمسك بيدي بإحكام ، متوسلاً لحياته.
You have had your share of troubles, doing things you do not even care about.
لقد كان لديك نصيب من المشاكل ، القيام بأشياء لا تهتم بها حتى.
Do not dare say I do not care about it.
لا تجرؤ على القول إنني لا أهتم بذلك.
Are you saying you really care about the wounded soldiers?
هل تقول أنك تهتم حقا بالجنود الجرحى؟
Of course I do.
بالطبع افعل.
I worried and got sad as if it had happened to me.
قلقت وحزنت كما لو أن ذلك حدث لي.
You should insist that the sun rose from the ground today.
يجب أن تصر على أن الشمس أشرقت من الأرض اليوم.
You are unbelievable.
أنت لا تصدق.
Why on earth are you so crooked?
لماذا بحق السماء أنت ملتوي؟
I am not as crooked as you, who likes a taken man.
أنا لست معوجًا مثلك ، يحب الرجل المأخوذ.
Hey!
يا!
Did you...
هل فعلت...
Did you just shout at me?
هل صرخت في وجهي للتو؟
You do it to me too.
أنت تفعل ذلك لي أيضا.
I...
أنا...
I am...
أنا أكون...
older than you too!
أكبر منك أيضًا!
Tell me.
أخبرني.
How did Young Master Yeon Jun end up getting so severely hurt?
كيف انتهى الأمر بالسيد الصغير يون جون إلى هذا الحد بأذى شديد؟
No.
لا.
What were you doing while Young Master...
ماذا كنت تفعل بينما يونغ ماستر ...
was getting himself injured?
كان يصاب نفسه؟
Lady Gil Chae.
سيدة جيل تشاي.
Is it my fault...
هل هو خطأي...
that Young Master Yeon Jun got hurt?
أن السيد الشاب يون جون تأذى؟
You said you know about the foreign intruders very well.
قلت أنك تعرف جيداً عن الدخلاء الأجانب.
If you are so knowledgeable and impressive,
إذا كنت واسع المعرفة ومثير للإعجاب ،
you should act accordingly!
يجب أن تتصرف وفقًا لذلك!
You pretended all high and mighty, but look at the state of you.
لقد تظاهرت بكل شيء عظيم وعظيم ، لكن انظر إلى حالتك.
The cut wound you had got infected.
الجرح الذي أصبت به.
I am fine.
أنا بخير.
I have to go back up.
لا بد لي من العودة.
Wait.
انتظر.
Gosh.
يا الهي.
Sit.
يجلس.
Do not think about going anywhere. Sit here tightly.
لا تفكر في الذهاب إلى أي مكان.  اجلس هنا بإحكام.
I said to sit there tightly.
قلت أن أجلس هناك بإحكام.
Gosh.
يا الهي.
Why is she making a fuss over something so small?
لماذا تثير ضجة حول شيء صغير جدًا؟
He got struck deep in his thigh.
أصيب بعمق في فخذه.
There is a chance...
هناك فرصة...
he might not be able to reproduce in the future.
قد لا يكون قادرًا على التكاثر في المستقبل.
- What?
- ماذا؟  - ماذا؟
It is fine.
انه بخير.
It does not matter.
لا تهم.
I am glad you are alive.
أنا سعيد لأنك على قيد الحياة.
Lady Eun Ae.
السيدة إيون آي.
I was wrong.
كنت مخطئ.
It missed it by a nose.
لقد فاتها من أنف.
He will be able to produce offspring after all.
سيكون قادرًا على إنتاج ذرية بعد كل شيء.
Thank goodness.
شكرا لله.
Young Master Jang Hyun.
السيد الشاب جانغ هيون.
I want to thank you for helping Young Master Yeon Jun.
أود أن أشكرك على مساعدة السيد الشاب يون جون.
I am not sure how I can repay you.
لست متأكدا كيف يمكنني السداد لك.
Well.
حسنًا.
I did not save them.
أنا لم أحفظهم.
He managed to survive longer than I thought.
تمكن من البقاء على قيد الحياة لفترة أطول مما كنت أعتقد.
I know you protected Young Master Yeon Jun.
أعلم أنك تحمي السيد الشاب يون جون.
He only studied his whole life so he is a bad fighter.
لقد درس حياته كلها فقط لذا فهو مقاتل سيء.
You must be upset that even I realized what Gil Chae did not.
يجب أن تكون منزعجًا لأنني أدركت ما لم يفعله جيل تشاي.
The other day, I told you to think about...
في ذلك اليوم ، أخبرتك أن تفكر في ...
who Gil Chae looked at during the wedding anniversary party.
الذي نظر إليه جيل تشاي خلال حفل ذكرى الزواج.
She looked at Young Master Yeon Jun.
نظرت إلى السيد الشاب يون جون.
Not that talk again.
ليس هذا الكلام مرة أخرى.
When one is shocked and scared,
عندما يشعر المرء بالصدمة والخوف ،
the one they look for is the one they truly love?
الشخص الذي يبحثون عنه هو الشخص الذي يحبونه حقًا؟
My lady.
سيدتي.
Is that not ridiculous in the first place?
أليس هذا سخيفا في المقام الأول؟
What kind of fool would fall for that...
أي نوع من الأحمق يقع في ذلك ...
She looked at you.
نظرت إليك.
Me? She looked at me?
أنا؟  نظرت إلي؟
Yes.
نعم.
Why, who do you think she was looking at?
لماذا ، من تعتقد أنها كانت تنظر؟
Young Master Yeon Jun?
السيد الشاب يون جون؟
Gil Chae may cherish him,
قد يعتز به جيل تشاي ،
but those feelings are not romantic.
لكن هذه المشاعر ليست رومانسية.
Go and ask her if you do not believe me.
اذهب واسألها إذا كنت لا تصدقني.
I may not be a physician,
قد لا أكون طبيبا ،
but with my experience from treating hundreds of soldiers,
لكن بخبرتي في علاج مئات الجنود ،
I can tell that this wound will not heal easily.
أستطيع أن أقول إن هذا الجرح لن يلتئم بسهولة.
You will have to rest here for a month at least.
سوف تضطر إلى الراحة هنا لمدة شهر على الأقل.
Do you wish for me to stay?
هل تتمنى أن أبقى؟
It is not my wish.
إنها ليست أمنيتي.
Your wound is just too severe.
جرحك شديد للغاية.
So this small, insignificant wound...
لذلك هذا الجرح الصغير غير المهم ...
desperately calls for your care and concern.
يدعو بشدة لرعايتك وقلقك.
Is that it?
هل هاذا هو؟
Oh, my goodness. You are bleeding.
يا إلهي.  أنت تنزف.
My goodness.
رباه.
It was already bleeding.
كان ينزف بالفعل.
That is not how Lady Eun Ae does it.
هذه ليست الطريقة التي تفعلها السيدة إيون آي.
I know how to do it too.
انا اعرف كيف افعلها ايضا
Everyone thinks Eun Ae is more competent than me.
يعتقد الجميع أن Eun Ae أكثر كفاءة مني.
But there are things I am better at.
لكن هناك أشياء أفضل فيها.
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
Lady Eun Ae told me something strange.
أخبرتني السيدة إيون آي شيئًا غريبًا.
During the wedding anniversary party in Neunggun-ri,
خلال حفل الذكرى السنوية للزواج في نيونغون ري ،
everyone was frantic at the news of the intruders.
كان الجميع مذعورين من أخبار المتسللين.
In that situation,
في هذه الحالة ،
you did not look at anyone else...
لم تنظر إلى أي شخص آخر ...
but me, is that true?
لكن هل هذا صحيح؟
Come to think of it, you are so lame.
تعال إلى التفكير في الأمر ، أنت أعرج للغاية.
The one you like is the one you look for when you are scared?
الشخص الذي يعجبك هو الذي تبحث عنه عندما تشعر بالخوف؟
Was that written in scripture?
هل كتب ذلك في الكتاب المقدس؟
You actually believe that?
هل تصدق ذلك بالفعل؟
Goodness. How ridiculous.
صلاح.  كم هذا سخيف.
Still,
ما زال،
I was the first one you looked at, yes?
كنت أول من نظرت إليه ، أليس كذلك؟
Even though you say you like another man,
على الرغم من أنك تقول أنك مثل رجل آخر ،
you looked at me during that state of chaos.
نظرت إليّ خلال تلك الحالة من الفوضى.
I feel bad that I have to turn you down.
أشعر بالسوء لأنني يجب أن أرفضك.
What?
ماذا؟
So let me suggest...
لذا اسمحوا لي أن أقترح ...
that we take on a broader perspective.
التي نأخذها من منظور أوسع.
The words "lover" and "nobody" are near each other in the dictionary.
الكلمتان "عاشق" و "لا أحد" قريبتان من بعضهما البعض في القاموس.
But do you know what is in between those two words?
لكن هل تعرف ما هو بين هاتين الكلمتين؟
"M" for "mull."
"M" تعني "mull".
There is space to mull.
هناك متسع للتفكير فيه.
If you do not know what you feel,
إذا كنت لا تعرف ما تشعر به ،
how about we take some time...
ماذا لو أخذنا بعض الوقت ...
to mull over our relationship?
للتفكير في علاقتنا؟
If a man and woman mull over their relationship,
إذا فكر رجل وامرأة في علاقتهما ،
they do not have to give each other an answer.
لا يتعين عليهم تقديم إجابة لبعضهم البعض.
Neither do they have to cut each other off right away.
لا يتعين عليهم قطع بعضهم البعض على الفور.
We can quietly look after each other...
يمكننا الاعتناء ببعضنا البعض بهدوء ...
and have fun from time to time.
واستمتع من وقت لآخر.
Then we can decide whether we want to be "lovers" or "nobodies," that is all.
ثم يمكننا أن نقرر ما إذا كنا نريد أن نكون "عشاق" أو "لا أحد" ، هذا كل شيء.
In that case,
في هذه الحالة،
until when do we mull about it?
حتى متى نفكر في ذلك؟
If one of us starts yearning desperately...
إذا بدأ أحدنا يتوق بشدة ...
or loses interest, we will call it off.
أو تفقد الفائدة ، سنلغيها.
Mull, my foot.
مول ، قدمي.
All this time you must have talked about misogamism...
كل هذا الوقت لا بد أنك تحدثت عن كره الزواج ...
and mulling to insult countless women.
والتفكير في إهانة عدد لا يحصى من النساء.
I can tell without looking.
أستطيع أن أقول دون النظر.
Do not even think of treating me like that.
لا تفكر في معاملتي بهذه الطريقة.
Wait, my...
انتظر يا ...
My lady.
سيدتي.
My goodness!
رباه!
Mulling is not something awful.
التفكير ليس شيئًا فظيعًا.
My lady. Are you there?
سيدتي.  هل أنت هناك؟
Are you sleeping?
هل أنت نائم؟
If you cannot sleep, do you want me to talk to you?
إذا لم تستطع النوم ، هل تريدني أن أتحدث معك؟
Is it a mere coincidence?
هل هي مجرد مصادفة؟
Whenever the moon is bright,
كلما كان القمر مضيئا ،
you are always by my side.
انت دائما بجانبي.
Now you will cross my mind whenever the moon is bright.
الآن سوف تخطر ببالي كلما كان القمر مشرقًا.
The others...
الاخرون...
Oh, my.
أوه يا.
It is you, Jong Jong.
إنه أنت يا جونغ جونغ.
Well...
حسنًا...
Are the others doing fine?
هل الآخرون بخير؟
The others?
الاخرون؟
I see.
أرى.
Handsome Ryang Eum is fine...
وسيم Ryang Eum بخير ...
so he does not have to come here.
لذلك ليس عليه المجيء إلى هنا.
Not Ryang Eum, I mean...
ليس Ryang Eum ، أعني ...
What has gotten to her?
ماذا حصل لها؟
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
I mean Lady Gil Chae.
أعني السيدة جيل تشاي.
The smell and discomfort made it hard...
الرائحة وعدم الراحة جعلت الأمر صعبًا ...
for her to sleep these days.
لتنام هذه الايام.
But she sleeps so soundly when she is with you.
لكنها تنام بهدوء عندما تكون معك.
When we met in the mountains, she also slept well.
عندما التقينا في الجبال ، كانت تنام جيدًا أيضًا.
Why does that happen?
لماذا يحدث ذلك؟
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
you do not have to send Gu Jam my regards or anything.
ليس عليك إرسال تحياتي أو أي شيء إلى Gu Jam.
I did not know snoring could sound so sweet.
لم أكن أعرف أن الشخير قد يبدو لطيفًا جدًا.
Dear me.
عزيزي.
Madam Bang Doo, please take a break.
سيدتي بانغ دو ، من فضلك خذي استراحة.
Everyone is working hard, how can I take a break?
الجميع يعمل بجد ، كيف يمكنني أخذ قسط من الراحة؟
I should help.
يجب أن أساعد.
My arm hurts!
ذراعي تألمني!
If these herbs can cure Young Master Yeon Jun,
إذا كانت هذه الأعشاب يمكن أن تشفي السيد الشاب يون جون ،
I do not care if my palms blister.
لا يهمني إذا كانت راحتي تتقرح.
My lady.
سيدتي.
This is not a herb.
هذه ليست عشب.
My, you have harvested a lot.
لقد حصدت الكثير.
Please let me.
ارجوك اتركني.
- Thank you. - Madam Bang Doo.
- شكرًا لك.  - سيدتي بانغ دو.
You are unwell. Do not carry such heavy things.
أنت لست على ما يرام.  لا تحمل مثل هذه الأشياء الثقيلة.
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
Mine is heavy too.
الألغام ثقيلة أيضًا.
Lady Eun Ae, this is a lot of precious herbs.
سيدة إيون آي ، هذا كثير من الأعشاب الثمينة.
How are you always so competent?
كيف حالك دائما مختص جدا؟
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
Lady Eun Ae, allow me.
سيدة إيون آي ، اسمح لي.
Allow me.
اسمح لي.
- Goodness.
- صلاح.  - صلاح.
Come over here.
تعال الى هنا.
I am fine.
أنا بخير.
Where are you going?
إلى أين تذهب؟
Why do you think I carried all those women across?
لماذا تعتقد أنني حملت كل هؤلاء النساء؟
When getting to know someone,
عند التعرف على شخص ما ،
you are supposed to help them across a stream like this.
من المفترض أن تساعدهم عبر تيار مثل هذا.
Then are you getting to know...
إذن هل ستعرف ...
all of those women too?
كل هؤلاء النساء أيضا؟
- No, it is different. - What is?
- لا ، الأمر مختلف.  - ما هو؟
My feelings.
مشاعري.
Those who have recovered from their wounds, come forward!
أولئك الذين شفوا من جراحهم تعالوا!
It is an all-out war!
إنها حرب شاملة!
Take action if you can walk!
اتخذ إجراءً إذا كنت تستطيع المشي!
Jong Jong asked about you.
سأل جونغ جونغ عنك.
Women...
نحيف...
are crazy about men if they are handsome.
مجنون بالرجال إذا كانوا وسيمين.
I was talking to you, not Ryang Eum.
كنت أتحدث إليكم ، وليس ريانغ إيوم.
Me?
أنا؟
Early in the morning, the people of our nation, who tried to hide,
في الصباح الباكر أهل أمتنا الذين حاولوا الاختباء ،
were killed by our enemies.
قتلهم أعداؤنا.
The monstrous intruders...
المتسللون المتوحشون ...
considered the lives of the Joseon people as light as a feather...
اعتبروا حياة شعب جوسون خفيفة كالريشة ...
and slaughtered everyone including the children and the elderly.
ويذبحون الجميع بمن فيهم الأطفال والشيوخ.
So what should we do?
اذا ماذا يجب ان نفعل؟
Who will rescue His Majesty...
من سينقذ جلالة الملك ...
and how will we protect the people of our nation?
وكيف نحمي أبناء أمتنا؟
However, do not be afraid.
ومع ذلك ، لا تخافوا.
What? Where did your ribbon go?
ماذا؟  أين ذهب الشريط الخاص بك؟
Although the reinforcement with provisions and weapons has not arrived yet,
على الرغم من أن التعزيزات بالمؤن والأسلحة لم تصل بعد ،
we have a single chance...
لدينا فرصة واحدة ...
to fight against them.
لمحاربتهم.
We are going to give it our all...
سوف نعطيها كل ما لدينا ...
from the last remaining soldier to the last arrowhead!
من آخر جندي متبقٍ إلى آخر رأس سهم!
- That means we are all going to die. - We will wait at the...
- هذا يعني أننا سنموت جميعًا.  - سننتظر عند ...
Hey, let us leave.
مهلا ، دعونا نغادر.
He says we are all going to die.
يقول أننا جميعًا سنموت.
This is where I shall die.
هذا هو المكان الذي سأموت فيه.
We will easily be able to defeat the intruders as the soldiers of Joseon...
سنكون قادرين بسهولة على هزيمة الدخلاء كجنود جوسون ...
You may leave and preserve your body.
يمكنك المغادرة والحفاظ على جسدك.
Thank you very much for your help.
شكرا جزيلا لك على مساعدتك.
We are not weak!
نحن لسنا ضعفاء!
Let us all...
دعونا جميعا ...
return His Majesty's favor with our lives.
رد صالح جلالة الملك بحياتنا.
Are you ready?
هل أنت جاهز؟
Look.
ينظر.
You should think of winning a victory.
يجب أن تفكر في الفوز بالنصر.
Why is everyone so determined to die while fighting?
لماذا الجميع مصممون على الموت أثناء القتال؟
Since we are already risking our lives,
بما أننا بالفعل نخاطر بحياتنا ،
should we not risk them for a fight that will end up in a victory?
ألا يجب المخاطرة بهم في معركة تنتهي بالنصر؟
You insolent...
أنت وقح ...
How dare you?
كيف تجرؤ؟
Is there a way...
هل هناك طريقة...
in which our soldiers can win without dying?
حيث يمكن لجنودنا أن ينتصروا دون أن يموتوا؟
Do you know what that smoke is?
هل تعرف ما هو هذا الدخان؟
Since you have fought against them for ten years in the northern provinces,
منذ أن حاربتهم لمدة عشر سنوات في الأقاليم الشمالية ،
you should be able to guess.
يجب أن تكون قادرًا على التخمين.
It is the smoke...
إنه الدخان ...
that appears after the intruders burn the bodies of dead soldiers.
الذي يظهر بعد قيام المتسللين بإحراق جثث القتلى.
The thing is,
الشيء هو،
the intruders feel proud of dying while fighting,
يشعر الدخلاء بالفخر بالموت أثناء القتال ،
but they find it ignoble to have their dead bodies...
لكنهم يجدون أنه من الدنيء أن تكون جثثهم ...
handed over to their enemies.
سلموا لأعدائهم.
Therefore,
لذلك،
no matter what,
بغض النظر،
they will not leave the corpses of their comrades in their enemy's camp.
لن يتركوا جثث رفاقهم في معسكر أعدائهم.
- Like our Manchurian ancestors
- مثل أسلافنا المنشوريين - مثل أسلافنا المنشوريين
- Let us shoot arrows
- لنرمي السهام - لنرمي السهام
- In this capricious world
- في هذا العالم المتقلب - في هذا العالم المتقلب
- You passed by in a flash
- مررت في ومضة - مررت في ومضة
- Let us go
- دعنا نذهب - لنذهب
- Let us go and shoot arrows
- دعونا نذهب ونطلق السهام - لنذهب ونطلق السهام
Everything we earned while fighting...
كل ما كسبناه أثناء القتال ...
will be shared with the family of those who lost their lives.
سيتم مشاركتها مع عائلة أولئك الذين فقدوا حياتهم.
So do not be afraid of death!
فلا تخافوا من الموت!
Those who die while fighting courageously...
الذين يموتون وهم يقاتلون بشجاعة ...
will live forever in His Majesty's glory.
ستعيش إلى الأبد في مجد جلالته.
Burn them.
احرقهم.
Stop him.
أوقفوه.
Right now!
الآن!
The enemy general is dead!
جنرال العدو مات!
Attack!
هجوم!
Kim Jun Ryong's army has won a great victory.
حقق جيش Kim Jun Ryong نصرا عظيما.
Also, Yangguri, the son-in-law of Nurhaci,
وأيضًا يانغجوري ، صهر نورهاسي ،
whom he cherished the most,
من كان يعتز به أكثر ،
died after being shot by a Joseon soldier.
توفي بعد أن أطلق عليه جندي جوسون النار.
We beat the intruders!
لقد تغلبنا على الدخلاء!
We defeated the Qing soldiers, so we bought ourselves some time.
لقد هزمنا جنود أسرة تشينغ ، لذلك اشترينا لأنفسنا بعض الوقت.
Once the reinforcements arrive, we will gather more power to stop the siege...
بمجرد وصول التعزيزات سنجمع المزيد من القوة لوقف الحصار ...
General!
عام!
The relieving force that was supposed to come with provisions and arrows...
القوة المخففة التي كان من المفترض أن تأتي بالمؤن والسهام ...
has been attacked by the Qing army.
تم مهاجمته من قبل جيش تشينغ.
Our source of reinforcements has been cut off.
تم قطع مصدر التعزيزات لدينا.
We must fight on,
يجب أن نقاتل ،
however, we cannot, for we ran out of arrows and provisions for battle.
ولكننا لا نستطيع ذلك ، فقد نفدت السهام والمؤن للحرب.
Thus, I shall assemble a vanguard today...
وهكذا ، سأجمع طليعة اليوم ...
and head for Suwon to gather supplies.
وتوجه إلى سوون لجمع المؤن.
The remaining men shall disperse...
يتفرق باقي الرجال ...
and each secure provisions and arrows,
وكل مؤن وسهام يؤمن ،
to ultimately rescue His Majesty from Namhan Fortress.
لإنقاذ جلالة الملك في نهاية المطاف من قلعة نامهان.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
What shall we do, Your Majesty?
ماذا سنفعل يا جلالة الملك؟
- Your Majesty.
- جلالة الملك.  - جلالة الملك.
(January 6th, Year of Jeongchuk, Disbandment of Kim Jun Ryong's Troops)
(6 يناير ، عام جيونغتشوك ، حل قوات كيم جون ريونغ)
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
I will go to the palace.
سأذهب إلى القصر.
I, Pyo Eon Kyum, am the senior eunuch...
أنا ، بيو إيون كيوم ، أنا الخصي الأكبر ...
who serves the Crown Prince.
الذي يخدم ولي العهد.
I came out to visit my mother and happened to run into the foreign intruders.
خرجت لزيارة والدتي وصادفت متسللين أجانب.
Now, I will head to the palace to deliver news...
الآن سأتوجه إلى القصر لإيصال الأخبار ...
of Mount Gwanggyo to His Majesty and the Crown Prince.
من جبل جوانجيو لجلالة الملك وولي العهد.
Who will accompany me?
من سيرافقني؟
I will go with you.
سوف اذهب معك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Is there anyone else?
هل هناك أي شخص آخر؟
Is there no one else...
لا يوجد أحد آخر...
willing to join me?
على استعداد للانضمام إلي؟
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
Will you just leave me to die?
هل ستتركني فقط لأموت؟
Why would you say that?
لماذا تريد ان تقول ذلك؟
If I were to encounter the foreign intruders and meet my end,
إذا واجهت الدخلاء الأجانب ولقيت نهايتي ،
my men would tell the Crown Prince I died...
سيخبر رجالي ولي العهد أنني مت ...
because you abandoned me.
لأنك تركتني.
People will think I am the foreign intruder then.
سيعتقد الناس أنني الدخيل الأجنبي حينها.
I heard you were dying to get an update about me.
سمعت أنك تتوق للحصول على تحديث عني.
I appreciate your affection, but I had a rather high standard.
أنا أقدر عاطفتك ، لكن كان لدي مستوى عالٍ إلى حد ما.
What are you saying?
ماذا تقول؟
Jong Jong.
الشباب الشباب.
What were you so curious about?
ما الذي كنت فضوليًا بشأنه؟
When the day breaks, I will leave.
عندما يأتي اليوم ، سأرحل.
I have decided to accompany the eunuch serving the Crown Prince.
لقد قررت مرافقة الخصي الذي يخدم ولي العهد.
Please understand.
من فضلك إفهم.
I can never...
لا أستطيع أبدا...
abandon His Majesty.
تتخلى عن جلالة الملك.
Right.
يمين.
What is happening?
ماذا يحدث؟
It is a rare occasion that you came to greet me.
إنها مناسبة نادرة أن أتيت لتحييني.
Right.
يمين.
Your turn is not coming.
دورك لن يأتي.
Should I call him for you?
هل يجب أن اتصل به من أجلك؟
- Young Master Yeon Jun... - Stop it. Will you?
- السيد الشاب يون جون ... - توقف.  سوف تفعل؟
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
why are you going?
لماذا انتي ذاهبة
You said you are not interested in rescuing the King.
قلت إنك غير مهتم بإنقاذ الملك.
I am not interested.
لست مهتما.
So why are you going?
فلماذا أنت ذاهب؟
You want to know the reason?
تريد أن تعرف السبب؟
What did you and Lady Gil Chae talk so long about?
ما الذي تحدثت عنه أنت والسيدة جيل تشاي لفترة طويلة؟
You chatted for quite some time.
لقد تحدثت لبعض الوقت.
Chat? You are getting ruder day by day.
محادثة؟  أنت تزداد فظاظة يوما بعد يوم.
By the way, my lady. Why do we have to go all the way there?
بالمناسبة سيدتي.  لماذا علينا الذهاب إلى هناك؟
Just push.
فقط ادفع.
Push harder.
ادفع بقوة أكبر.
It is an ambush!
إنه كمين!
- What are you doing? - I protect His Highness,
- ماذا تفعل؟  - أنا أحمي سموه ،
so protecting me is like protecting His Highness.
لذا فإن حمايتي مثل حماية سموه.
Stop it!
توقف عن ذلك!
- Give it to me. - What are you doing?
- اعطني اياه.  - ماذا تفعل؟
Come on.
تعال.
Stop it.
توقف عن ذلك.
What is going on?
ما الذي يجري؟
Everyone must be headed there.
يجب أن يتجه الجميع إلى هناك.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
Must we go there too?
هل يجب أن نذهب إلى هناك أيضًا؟
Yes. We must go.
نعم.  يجب أن نذهب.
We must.
يجب علينا أن.
Go.
يذهب.
The foreign intruders erected wooden stakes...
نصب المتسللون الأجانب أوتاد خشبية ...
and placed bells on top of them, blocking any possible leakage points.
ووضع أجراس فوقها لمنع أي نقاط تسرب محتملة.
But they are also human. There must be vulnerabilities.
لكنهم بشر أيضًا.  يجب أن تكون هناك نقاط ضعف.
The monk soldiers have been moving in and out of the fortress.
كان الجنود الراهبون يتنقلون داخل القلعة وخارجها.
Then can I truly meet His Majesty?
ثم هل يمكنني حقا أن ألتقي جلالة الملك؟
In ordinary times, you might never dare to request to see him.
في الأوقات العادية ، قد لا تجرؤ أبدًا على طلب مقابلته.
However, after breaking through death itself to enter the fortress,
ومع ذلك ، بعد أن كسر الموت نفسه لدخول الحصن ،
how could His Majesty refuse to see you?
كيف يرفض جلالة الملك أن يراك؟
Wait.
انتظر.
It is ready. Let us go.
إنه جاهز.  دعنا نذهب.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
Your Majesty, I am overjoyed to see you being safe and sound.
جلالة الملك ، أنا مسرور للغاية لرؤيتك بخير وبصحة جيدة.
- I could die today... - Thank you.
- يمكن أن أموت اليوم ... - شكرا لك.
I am very proud of you.
أنا فخور بك.
Even among the men who are employed by the government,
حتى بين الرجال الذين توظفهم الحكومة ،
there are many people who ran away...
هناك الكثير من الناس الذين هربوا ...
because they were afraid of dying at the fortress.
لأنهم كانوا خائفين من الموت في الحصن.
And yet you risked your life to rescue me.
ومع ذلك فقد خاطرت بحياتك لإنقاذي.
Look.
ينظر.
As long as we have scholars like these in Joseon,
طالما لدينا علماء مثل هؤلاء في جوسون ،
our government will be preserved.
سيتم الحفاظ على حكومتنا.
It will be preserved for all times to come.
سيتم الحفاظ عليها في جميع الأوقات القادمة.
You are right, Your Majesty.
أنت على حق يا جلالة الملك.
This is a big blessing for our nation.
هذه نعمة كبيرة لأمتنا.
- It is a big blessing,
- إنها نعمة كبيرة - إنها نعمة كبيرة ،
- Your Majesty.
- جلالة الملك.  - جلالة الملك.
Right.
يمين.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
Now that the scholars have brought back the heads of the foreign intruders,
والآن بعد أن أعاد العلماء رؤوس المتسللين الأجانب ،
Joseon's spirit is alive.
روح جوسون حية.
Please do not lose your hope...
من فضلك لا تفقد الأمل ...
and spur on the troops around the fortress...
وتحفيز القوات حول القلعة ...
Minister Kim, do the Neunggun-ri scholars look like hope to you?
معالي الوزير كيم ، هل يبدو علماء نيونغون ري مثل الأمل بالنسبة لك؟
General Jung's army of 15,000 have all been dispersed...
تم تفريق جيش الجنرال يونغ البالغ قوامه 15000 فرد ...
and only seven of them made it back.
واستعادها سبعة منهم فقط.
They are proof that the royal forces are stuck.
إنها دليل على أن القوات الملكية عالقة.
In such a dire situation,
في مثل هذه الحالة الأليمة ،
words are not enough.
الكلمات لا تكفي.
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك ،
since all the royal forces are stuck,
بما أن جميع القوات الملكية عالقة ،
we have to send an envoy and tell them our intent for mediation.
علينا إرسال مبعوث وإخبارهم بنيتنا في الوساطة.
Will they...
سوف ...
agree to mediation?
توافق على الوساطة؟
Since the old days,
منذ الايام الخوالي
invading deep into the enemy's land...
غزو ​​عمق أرض العدو ...
has been the final military resort.
كان الملاذ العسكري الأخير.
I am sure that...
أنا متأكد من أن ...
they also wish for mediation.
هم أيضا يرغبون في الوساطة.
It is too early for mediation...
الوقت مبكر للوساطة ...
or sending out all our troops to war.
أو إرسال كل قواتنا للحرب.
Before that,
قبل ذلك،
have our forces reached their camp with wine and meat?
هل وصلت قواتنا إلى معسكرهم بالنبيذ واللحوم؟
We appreciate the thought.
نحن نقدر الفكر.
But all the poultry and crops of Joseon belong to us now.
لكن كل دواجن ومحاصيل جوسون ملكنا الآن.
Why would we need any of these?
لماذا نحتاج إلى أي من هؤلاء؟
From now on,
من الان فصاعدا،
I have nothing to discuss about our countries.
ليس لدي ما أناقشه بشأن بلداننا.
His Majesty...
جلالته...
is on his way.
هو في طريقه.
Is that true...
هل هذا صحيح...
that Khan has arrived?
أن خان قد وصل؟
I cannot be sure.
لا أستطيع أن أكون متأكدا.
The Jin are still at war with the Ming,
جين لا يزالون في حالة حرب مع مينغ ،
so how is it possible that Khan...
فكيف يعقل أن خان ...
would enter Joseon instead of fighting the Ming?
هل ستدخل جوسون بدلاً من محاربة مينغ؟
How long do they intend to stay in the fortress?
كم من الوقت ينوون البقاء في القلعة؟
The Ming troops held out for 82 days at Dalinghe.
صمدت قوات مينغ لمدة 82 يومًا في دالينجي.
So they will also...
لذلك سوف ...
Eighty days?
ثمانون يوما؟
There is no way that Khan is here.
لا توجد طريقة أن يكون خان هنا.
They must be bluffing.
يجب أن يكونوا مخادعين.
However,
لكن،
if Khan is really here...
إذا كان خان حقاً هنا ...
If only there was someone who knows the minds of the Jin well.
لو كان هناك فقط شخص يعرف عقول جين جيداً.
I do...
أفعل...
know someone.
تعرف شخصا.
Our next battle may happen soon...
قد تحدث معركتنا القادمة قريبًا ...
so work hard and mend them now.
لذا اعمل بجد وأصلحهم الآن.
What a diligent chap.
يا له من فصل مجتهد.
Do you not like him because he is diligent?
ألا تحبه لأنه مجتهد؟
That is why the ladies love him.
هذا هو السبب في أن السيدات تحبه.
He has a face that ladies love.
لديه وجه تحبه السيدات.
What do you mean by that?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
How should I put it?
كيف يجب ان اضعها؟
He looks like the faithful type that will only love one woman.
إنه يشبه النوع المخلص الذي سيحب امرأة واحدة فقط.
Unlike someone I know.
على عكس شخص أعرفه.
You mean, he looks like a swindler.
تقصد ، يبدو وكأنه نصاب.
- He will hear. - Let him hear.
- سوف يسمع.  - دعه يسمع.
Did I say anything wrong?
هل قلت شيئا خاطئا؟
Look at him smile.
انظر إليه وهو يبتسم.
He looks more like a swindler now.
يبدو الآن وكأنه نصاب.
You. We need to talk.
أنت.  يجب أن نتكلم.
It must have been tough getting here.
يجب أن يكون الوصول إلى هنا صعبًا.
No, Your Highness.
لا يا صاحب السمو.
I arrived safely thanks to the monk soldier who guided me.
وصلت بسلام بفضل الجندي الراهب الذي أرشدني.
Is that so?
هل هذا صحيح؟
Seems like the monks are useful in times like this.
يبدو أن الرهبان مفيدون في أوقات كهذه.
Yes, Your Highness.
نعم سموكم.
The bald men have become useful now that there is a war.
أصبح الرجال الصلع نافعين الآن بعد أن نشبت حرب.
Before that,
قبل ذلك،
they only made tofu and paper for the noble...
لقد صنعوا فقط التوفو والورق للنبلاء ...
and got beat up at times.
وتعرضوا للضرب في بعض الأحيان.
What other use would they have?
ما هي الاستخدامات الأخرى التي قد يكون لديهم؟
But it is strange, is it not?
لكن هذا غريب ، أليس كذلك؟
The country looks down on these monks.
البلد ينظر إلى هؤلاء الرهبان بازدراء.
How is it that once the country is in danger,
كيف يكون ذلك حال البلد في خطر ،
those people put their lives on the line to fight...
هؤلاء الناس وضعوا حياتهم على المحك للقتال ...
till their bald heads glisten with sweat?
حتى تتلألأ رؤوسهم الصلعاء بالعرق؟
- Hey, you! - Oh, dear.
- يا هذا!  - يا عزيزي.
My apologies.
اعتذاري.
I speak without thinking, you see.
أنا أتكلم بدون تفكير ، كما ترى.
I applaud you for coming here at the risk of your lives.
أنا أحييك لمجيئك إلى هنا مخاطرة بحياتك.
But why is it just you folks?
لكن لماذا أنت فقط يا رفاق؟
I am greatly disappointed.
أشعر بخيبة أمل كبيرة.
His Majesty is here.
جلالة الملك هنا.
How can the people of Joseon take their time...
كيف يمكن لشعب جوسون أن يأخذوا وقتهم ...
and prioritize their own lives?
وتحديد أولويات حياتهم؟
At first,
في البدايه،
you did not want to come, did you?
انت لا تريد ان تاتي اليس كذلك؟
Did you also think that coming to the fortress meant your death?
هل تعتقد أيضًا أن القدوم إلى القلعة يعني موتك؟
I did not.
لم أفعل.
Then,
ثم،
did you think our court was foolish...
هل كنت تعتقد أن بلاطنا كان أحمق ...
for being tricked by the Jin?
لكونه خدع من قبل جين؟
That is not the case.
ليس هذا هو الحال.
His Majesty...
جلالته...
is wise enough to flee before the people did.
من الحكمة أن تهرب قبل أن يهرب الناس.
I did not think he needed my lowly help...
لم أكن أعتقد أنه بحاجة إلى مساعدتي المتواضعة ...
Your Highness!
صاحب السمو!
His Majesty is not any common folk.
جلالة الملك ليس أي قوم عادي.
Protecting his royal body...
حماية جسده الملكي ...
is not just protecting the life of a person.
لا يقتصر الأمر على حماية حياة الإنسان فقط.
His Majesty is Joseon.
جلالة الملك هو جوسون.
To protect him means to protect Joseon society.
لحمايته تعني حماية مجتمع جوسون.
Are you...
أنت...
Are you that foolish not to comprehend that?
هل أنت من الغباء أن لا تفهم ذلك؟
Are you that ignorant not to know that?
هل أنت ذلك الجاهل لعدم معرفة ذلك؟
How dare you send such a fool to me?
كيف تجرؤ على إرسال مثل هذا الأحمق إلي؟
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
I have sinned.
لقد أذنبت.
Kick him out.
اطرده.
Go and...
اذهب و...
get rid of him so I never have to see him again.
تخلص منه حتى لا أراه مرة أخرى.
You fool!
يالك من أحمق!
How dare you say that to His Highness?
كيف تجرؤ على قول ذلك لسمو؟
So why did you bother calling me?
فلماذا عناء الاتصال بي؟
I saw it.
رأيته.
Our troops won under your lead when we fought against Yangguri.
انتصرت قواتنا تحت قيادتك عندما قاتلنا ضد يانغوري.
In the end,
في النهاية،
we still split up without getting reinforcements.
ما زلنا نتفرق دون الحصول على تعزيزات.
You wasted your time.
لقد ضيعت وقتك.
No.
لا.
You earned us time...
لقد كسبت لنا الوقت ...
and the refugees nearby were able to flee.
وتمكن اللاجئون القريبون من الفرار.
You and the volunteer army...
أنت والجيش المتطوع ...
saved hundreds of innocent lives.
أنقذت مئات الأرواح البريئة.
When it comes to protecting people's lives,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بحماية حياة الناس ،
you are serious.
انت جاد.
That is why you lashed out at His Highness.
لهذا السبب انتقدت سموه.
But...
لكن...
the people have your compassion.
الناس رحمتك.
Did I see wrong?
هل رأيت خطأ؟
Rumor has it that Khan is here.
تقول الشائعات أن خان موجود هنا.
Although, we cannot be sure.
على الرغم من أننا لا نستطيع أن نكون متأكدين.
We tried to learn through an envoy,
حاولنا التعلم من خلال مبعوث ،
but he would not meet with us since Khan is touring Jin.
لكنه لم يقابلنا لأن خان يقوم بجولة في جين.
It must be a lie.
يجب أن تكون كذبة.
However,
لكن،
if Khan is really here,
إذا كان خان حقاً هنا ،
will the people of Joseon be fine?
هل سيكون شعب جوسون بخير؟
Where were you?
أين كنت؟
How did you get injured?
كيف أصبت؟
Goodness.
صلاح.
Seems like Khan is here.
يبدو أن خان هنا.
What?
ماذا؟
No way.
مستحيل.
It is a rumor.
إنها شائعة.
- But... - If Khan came here himself,
- لكن ... - إذا جاء خان إلى هنا بنفسه ،
he might be out to destroy Joseon completely.
قد يكون في الخارج لتدمير جوسون بالكامل.
We should not be here. Let us leave the fortress and flee Joseon.
لا ينبغي أن نكون هنا.  دعونا نغادر القلعة ونهرب من جوسون.
We only planned to lead Young Master Yeon Jun here safely.
لقد خططنا فقط لقيادة السيد الشاب يون جون هنا بأمان.
Lady Eun Ae told me something strange.
أخبرتني السيدة إيون آي شيئًا غريبًا.
In that situation,
في هذه الحالة ،
you did not look at anyone else...
لم تنظر إلى أي شخص آخر ...
but me,
لكن انا،
is that true?
هل هذا صحيح؟
Still,
ما زال،
I was the first one you looked at, yes?
كنت أول من نظرت إليه ، أليس كذلك؟
Darn it.
رتقها.
I plan to visit Jin's military camp.
أخطط لزيارة معسكر جين العسكري.
(Nojin: Jin's military camp)
(Nojin: معسكر جين العسكري)
What?
ماذا؟
If Khan is really here,
إذا كان خان حقاً هنا ،
why is he risking his life...
لماذا يخاطر بحياته ...
to be here while they are still at war with the Ming?
أن أكون هنا بينما هم لا يزالون في حالة حرب مع مينغ؟
I shall go and find out.
سأذهب واكتشف.
Is that not what you want to know?
أليس هذا ما تريد أن تعرفه؟
If you do that, His Majesty will be pleased...
إذا قمت بذلك ، فسيكون جلالته مسرورًا ...
I am not doing it to please His Majesty.
أنا لا أفعل ذلك لإرضاء جلالة الملك.
There are two things in this world that should not be left to last a long time.
هناك شيئان في هذا العالم لا ينبغي تركهما لوقت طويل.
The time spent on a toilet...
الوقت الذي يقضيه في المرحاض ...
and war.
والحرب.
If I find out some useful information,
إذا اكتشفت بعض المعلومات المفيدة ،
I am saying you should use it to end the war.
أنا أقول أنه يجب عليك استخدامها لإنهاء الحرب.
Of course.
بالطبع.
Tell me everything you need.
قل لي كل ما تحتاجه.
I do not need anything.
انا لا احتاج اي شي.
I just need Ryang Eum.
أنا فقط بحاجة إلى Ryang Eum.
For every armed intruder, there are one or two porters...
لكل دخيل مسلح واحد أو اثنان من الحمالين ...
who follow them around.
من يتبعهم.
When porters are wounded or killed,
عندما يُجرح الحمالون أو يُقتلون ،
they are often left behind.
غالبًا ما يتم تركهم وراءهم.
Ryang Eum and I will become abandoned porters.
سوف نصبح أنا و Ryang Eum حمالين مهجورين.
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
why are you going?
لماذا انتي ذاهبة
You said you are not interested in rescuing the King.
قلت إنك غير مهتم بإنقاذ الملك.
You want to know the reason?
تريد أن تعرف السبب؟
The thing is,
الشيء هو،
I do not want to see you cry.
لا اريد ان اراك تبكي.
Are you saying you are going because you do not want to see me?
هل تقول أنك ذاهب لأنك لا تريد رؤيتي؟
That is the same thing.
هذا هو نفس الشيء.
Also, how do you even know...
أيضا ، كيف تعرف حتى ...
when I will cry?
متى ابكي
There is something like that.
هناك شيء من هذا القبيل.
Right.
يمين.
I must ask you to do something.
يجب أن أطلب منك القيام بشيء ما.
Since the Mongolian soldiers are everywhere,
بما أن الجنود المنغوليين في كل مكان ،
go to Ganghwa Island.
اذهب إلى جزيرة كانغهوا.
The intruders are strong on land, but they are weak on water.
الدخلاء أقوياء على الأرض ، لكنهم ضعفاء في الماء.
That is why the King has a lot of cannons and provisions stored in Ganghwa Island.
هذا هو السبب في أن الملك لديه الكثير من المدافع والأحكام المخزنة في جزيرة كانغهوا.
Even his eldest grandson is there.
حتى حفيده الأكبر موجود هناك.
(Wonson: the king's grandson, the Crown Prince's eldest son)
(وونسون: حفيد الملك ، الابن البكر لولي العهد)
Even if Joseon becomes the enemy's den,
حتى لو أصبحت جوسون وكر العدو ،
you will be safe on Ganghwa Island.
ستكون بأمان في جزيرة كانغهوا.
I now see that mulling is...
أرى الآن أن التفكير هو ...
a method used by irresponsible people to make it easy for them to slip away.
طريقة يستخدمها أشخاص غير مسؤولين لتسهيل هروبهم.
Do not worry about me.
لا تقلق علي.
You are not interested anyway, are you?
أنت غير مهتم على أي حال ، أليس كذلك؟
You know very well that we are and will be suffering,
أنت تعلم جيدًا أننا نعاني وسوف نعاني ،
but you are choosing to flee again.
لكنك تختار الفرار مرة أخرى.
Then let us do this.
ثم دعونا نفعل هذا.
I swear by the moonlight.
أقسم بضوء القمر.
Go to Ganghwa Island.
اذهب إلى جزيرة كانغهوا.
This time, wherever you are,
هذه المرة ، أينما كنت ،
I will make sure...
سوف اتاكد...
I find you.
وجدتك.
(My Dearest)
(أعز ما عندي)
I received a letter from Jang Hyun.
لقد تلقيت رسالة من جانغ هيون.
It looks like something urgent has happened to the enemies.
يبدو أن شيئًا ما عاجلاً قد حدث للأعداء.
You were trying to get on that boat, right?
كنت تحاول ركوب ذلك القارب ، أليس كذلك؟
Let us get on that boat as well.
دعونا نركب هذا القارب أيضًا.
My lady, I do not want to die.
سيدتي ، لا أريد أن أموت.
You guys should go to the boat first.
يا رفاق يجب أن تذهب إلى القارب أولاً.
Then, the people who were on that boat...
ثم ، الأشخاص الذين كانوا على ذلك القارب ...
Send a boat to Ganghwa Island.
أرسل قاربًا إلى جزيرة كانغهوا.
Do not come. This boat is not for you!
لا تأتي.  هذا القارب ليس لك!
I need to check with my own eyes.
أنا بحاجة إلى التحقق بأم عيني.
Run away!
اهرب!
The intruders are coming!
الدخلاء قادمون!
I am here to fight a battle that I will not nor can lose.
أنا هنا لأخوض معركة لن أخسرها ولن أخسرها.
Please.
لو سمحت.
From now on, no one can cross this point.
من الآن فصاعدًا ، لا يمكن لأحد تجاوز هذه النقطة.
Ripped by YoungJedi
ممزق من قبل YoungJedi